[music]
Hello friends And today again
at 20 in the podcast, currently untitled, we
meet in the audio living room where the
shelves are filled with books, the carpets are soft And the
audio wine is especially pleasant to drink and
Here next to me in this audio living room is
Bohdana Neborak and I am Anastasia Yevdokymova with you
and we are glad to see and hear everyone
like this Hello, friends, we have seen and heard each other
for these 20 episodes, we have become very close to many people,
because at the
moment, without a name, it is always an opportunity for
discussion, it is not just a voice that
sounds by itself, first of all Because there are two of us, of
course, but also because we
discuss books together with you, we
discuss the most difficult and most
controversial together with you and for us.
It is important not to stop in this process. In the
19th episode, we talked about how we
speak and It was one a conversation about one
language, of course, about Ukrainian, and after such a
conversation, we want to read poetic
texts about language, about the Ukrainian language, about our
native language, about a word, about a book in which there is a
word about a bug about different images
related to the language and actually how
Ukrainian writers of the
19th-20th-21st centuries understood the language, you know, Nastya, I thought
about the fact that in Frankivsk you and I
talked about the Ukrainian language,
instead we are recording this poetic episode
in Kosovo in Ivano-Frankivsk region, and
as you and I found out, it is from the
Kosiv district that there is the largest number of
laureates of the Shevchenko Prize for poets, and
here you can simply go from
Frankivsk to Kosov and, passing a
lot of villages, list
Dmytro Pavlychko from here, Taras Melnychuk from here,
Vasyl Gerasimyuk will return there,
and from another village there will be Ivan Malkovich, and so
on and so on. Therefore, this is a very fertile
ground for finally
talking about poetry, because all these people are
the poets whom you listed, and they
actually worked the most with the
plasticity of language. We quote Ivan Malkovich's poem
in 19 -th episode And it is so
important that the
texts of the representatives of this region
sound in our podcast Yes And we also have
it's good to talk here when we see
our beautiful mountains the Carpathians outside the window
Let's go Yes, the Carpathians are fun The Carpathians
here here here here
in the Carpathians
touch the Carpathians with your hand this is a beast
and young years of friends there is a lot of breathing
[music]
son ​​can you beat a dead rooster for
tuning
[music]
Verkhovyna native mother is like dying
I think it is worth starting with the text of Vasyl
Holoborodek the author of 70 authors, are there any
texts?
institutions and Vasyl
Holoborodko is a name that many people know
from the series Servant of the People Because that is the name of
the president in this series, but
in fact for us it is a poet from Luhansk region, a
poet who wrote in particular the poem Our language,
which I will now quote Every word of our
language is sung in a song,
so we talk with our brothers in song with the words of the song
Every word of our
language is recorded in the annals, so let the
enemies know What we are silent with words alone,
this is a super poetic text that
mesmerizes me because it contains the two bases from
which language grows, when we talk about
language, there is actually some kind of beginning
where it begins, it does not
arise from nowhere, it does not
appear like dew on a leaf in the morning
on every blade of grass. It has a huge,
long history. The history of the Ukrainian
language begins.
Well, there different linguists will argue,
but from Kyivan Rus, roughly speaking, but
in fact even before the ancient times, and when we
talk about the fact that every word of the language is
sung in a song,
we are already mentioning folklore. in the previous
episodes, we mentioned folk songs and
it is so important to know the folk songs of your
region, to know the folk songs
dedicated to one or another topic, and to
remember that a song is what absorbed the
wisdom of the people, and the annals is what
absorbed the history of the people. Because when we
talk about the Ukrainian language is the day of the
Ukrainian language and writing, when on
November 9, the day of the death of
Nestor the Chronicler, we do not know my d
birth, we only know the day of death,
why Nestor the Chronicler and the Ukrainian language
are on the same line because Nestor the
Chronicler is one of the first
chroniclers, one of the first historians,
writers who recorded not only
historical realities, but also the history of the
monastery, the history of the people, the history of the princely
family, one of the first writers who
worked with fiction from those
writers then went to our days and
about whom we know from the history of literature.
I am sure that there were many who
sank into oblivion and time forgot about them and our
Our language begins with these two foundations from a
song from the chronicle and in the annals have written
words with which we can even remain silent
because if the annals answer about the
princes and their princes between individuals about
their conflicts about their victories and
defeats, then these are also the victories and
defeats of the Ukrainian statesmen not only
those who were then in the princely times in the 11th-12th
century but these are also certain lessons that were later
repeated or not rakes on which the
next offensive of the Ukrainian state because
history moves in these circles. I really
like how in this short
text Holoborodko does what he
actually does very well in all
poetry. And it speaks next to something
global about something very private.
Because Ukrainian song and especially
Ukrainian folk song This is what
accompanies the most important
moments of life, it can be a lullaby that a
mother sings to a child, it can be a song
around a newborn, it can be a
wedding song, it will be freckles, it
will be Christmas songs, it will eventually
be songs that are sung to send them
off to the other world,
and Language is also something very private, it is
what the closest thing to you And this is what you
explain the world to yourself, that is, if it is
easiest to say Language is a system of
signs, but
Holoborodko because of this
temporal depth that he chooses Is it a
song Is it an annals He shows
how ancient this
system of signs is, which can seem
very modern to us because we speak it We are here and
now,
you know, I wanted to choose the texts differently,
only by myself I will read it, but since you
started it, I want to somehow continue
a certain story that you suggest, and that is why I
will start with a text about the language with which I
really wanted to end, because it is
also about the language with which we are silent, and
in fact about very
sensitive things.
trodden snow winter
slows down stream Who is reading this you
is me who is reading this you like a poem
you speak you speak you ask you speak the
last of the secrets read sharp
metaphors of your collarbones
read moles and vertebrae the color of tin in
milk
Braille read at random fingers
acquired knowledge teach me Braille light
teaches like a book read her at night with
warm veins, her long seam is a list of those who
left her
as they touch the pages written off with the names of
women
found in closets, notebooks with the addresses of
betrayed husbands,
this is I read you like writing This is me speaking to
you, the darkness, the grammar of the read forearms of
your fonts, September night, the language that I am
I am silent in my
youth and I am crying in the language of a line on a quiet
river these sit at the table in silence, these
no one will say, no one will surrender, they
read the book on your wrists, they
read the family letters with scars, it is you who speak,
God, it is you, it is you who represents the fabric of writing from which winter is spelled,
into which
spring letters consonants and vowels are cut, it is
you who give names it is you who brings out like light from
darkness voices from deep silences I do not
understand your teachings the
grammar of wonder and winter Who loves it all
night this We
slowly read to the end the light
touches her face
this is a text from 2017 and I really
like how Zhadan combines here
several important for myself,
above all, this text can simply be read
as erotic love poetry. There will also be the
keys to this scar and what is supposedly
understandable without words.
At the same time, for me, it is the most expressive poem of
desire, which combines
a very private line of relations between a
man and a woman and a line of trying to
understand each other for In order to understand each other
, language is necessary. In
general, poems seem to me to be
more and more philological over the years
philological, he writes a lot
about spelling and syntax, and one of the latest
books, and perhaps the most recent book of his
translations in America, is called the new
spelling where I spell
Zhadan is constantly trying to understand
what these constructions are with which we convey
things important to us to others and through
which constructions we explain these important
things for ourselves and specifically. In this
text, I am incredibly impressed by how at
first it seems to you that I am a lyrical hero
who appeals to a lyrical heroine, and then
he begins to appeal to something much more
ancient behind this heroine,
although it is obvious that we are also talking about
conditional saying, picking the vertebrae of a
beloved creature and he goes incredibly deep
into the topic of this
understanding of existence as a distance and then
very sharply turns you back, let's say
, the bed itself, and
I'm really interested in how
Zhadan will move further in these
experiments on understanding language, because for
me it is one of some
key fragments of his poetry are from
one ancient vi rsha about the fact that between
what you say and how you are
understood is all poetry, that is,
poetry in misunderstanding, on the other hand, in this
text I read rather a
great desire to understand, a
great desire to understand and a great
anxiety from the fact that in reality complete
understanding is impossible and this must be
accepted but we want at least somehow an
extremely Great understanding of an extremely
Great immersion and again this
transition from the separate to the general and
in particular language and literature as that in which
language is expressed allows us such an
immersion in the rye there are many self-
repetitions in this text In principle, we
follow this because there were the first
collections of Maradona Ethiopia quote book
somewhere probably firearms knife close
to Maria's life we ​​see the origin of all the
texts then appear consonants
vowels of which there are so many there is a
wrist there is her black hair her black
underwear but these self-repetitions I
think I just talked about it I thought it was the
repetition of certain codes of yours that you
want to repeat
endlessly read them in order to
remember them, understand them,
read them and perceive them clearly,
because you have now read one text, and then
we can randomly open any
collection, read another text, and somewhere the
text already sounds, Dana is set to
music, and there will be the third text But
again, the same forms are such a certain
archetype in something, even which
at first I tried to explain as a certain
fraud, they say Serhiy Viktorovych
continues to write about what he already
wrote about But Zhadan quickly
admitted himself that he is really interested in large
plots that explain small ones the stories are the child
on the contrary and sometimes it is not necessarily the image of the
Virgin Mary And it really can be
for example This woman with hair as black as the earth
and he does what we can't
do We for example we can't find
our name and that's why our podcast
is called currently untitled instead,
Zhadan is constantly looking for what to call, what
names to give, and there are even these words that you
give names. But you and I, for example,
Bohdan does not know atni give these names But why
does Zhadan give names because he has a language because
if you have your own language you can name
and the peculiarity of this is what we are
actually talking about all this time That when
there is no language of your own there is no way
to speak, you cannot name me I will
kill you, but I remembered about it. There is a very
cool text that Zhadan wrote for the
foxtrots. Foxtrot is a big project of the
Art Arsenal. Oksana Shur was the decorator
and
it is tied to the texts of the Ukrainian
avant-garde, and there is such a unifying
text that Zhadan wrote. also became a
song, a modem link to it, which
is called seems to be a dead poet, and there
are lines approximately such that
no one but you will name the rivers around you. That is,
we understand that there is no language vacuum,
it cannot be that there is no language, there is
either one or the other or a third or the fifth,
but it is very important to give these names, and well,
in particular, poets do this and give names
to those processes and phenomena that
were in the past, so he turns to
this mine logo, he wants to remember how
previous generations breathed, how
grandparents and great-grandparents and great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-grandfather cried and He wants to
understand what kind of language we are silent in,
what kind of language we are silent in, it is the language of
our history, it is the language of ours,
it is our native language, then in fact I sometimes
ask of my acquaintances who switch from one
language to another, and it is not necessarily a duet of
Russian and Ukrainian.
What language do they think, but I allow
myself this question only with someone close
to close friends, because they consider it
quite intimate and so insidious, but there are
friends for whom it is even it was a bit stressful,
but then they admitted that they were saying that
you asked me about it there a year or two
ago and today I can tell you that I,
for example, started to think in Ukrainian, it
works in the end, he continues the language in which I am
silent, the language of breathing and crying, that is, the language in
which you breathe, the language how do you cry i.e.
when you are devoted or certain emotions or you are
so calm and relaxed that you
cannot control your subconscious
once one of my girlfriends read that
our native language is the one we speak
to ourselves or to other characters in
our words and she tried to understand for a long time
and she went to bed
thinking that I have to find out what language
I speak in my unconscious and
talks to me and she realized that
she is silent in her dreams, she and all the characters
around are also silent, they understand each
other at some level of touch of
glances and simply know what will happen
next, but in us she asked herself this question
because it was important to her, she expected that
somewhere subconsciously he was preparing her for it
is somehow a betrayal of the well-known scandalous essay by Taras
Prokhaska, which seems to be
called What language do you see dreams in? And
it caused a very ambiguous reaction,
but this only shows that when we
talk about language in the context of
our subconscious, the topic is very
dramatic. Language is a means of protection. It
can be yes, but also a means of understanding,
first of all, I think that when we talk
about language today, we
think about it through selected texts in
very, very different contexts tah,
but since we chose
Ukrainian-language texts and texts by Ukrainian
authors about the Ukrainian language
, the emphasis is already on the communication
function. Language is a way. Also, in order
to protect yourself, to defend yourself, because
one of the programmatic and programmatic texts of
Lesya Ukrainka is a poem, the word "why don't you"
hard wings from the collection of thoughts and dreams and
in this text the language Or rather the word
Every spoken word can turn
into a dangerous weapon the
word why are you not a hard cry What in the middle of the
battle will spark so clearly Why are you not a sharp
merciless sword the one who lifted the enemy's
heads from the shoulders you are mine sincere, hardened speech,
I will extract you from the scabbard, I am ready. Only you will spill the
blood from my heart, but you will not pierce the enemy's
heart with a blade.
I am a weapon. We must not both perish,
maybe in the hands of unknown brothers,
you will become the best sword for the executioners, the tyrant of the
lynx against the iron of the shackles, the moon will go along the
strongholds of the titans it
will rush with the clatter of other swords with the
sound of new things that are not prisons. The
strong avengers will accept my weapon and rush with it
bravely into battle.
far and she says
that the word is a sword, it is hard, it can
hit, it can impress, and the most important thing is
that it should be in the hands of those who are able to
hold this sword, in whose hands are
strong enough and who can grasp the hilt and know
where to hit, besides that to not just
wave this sword, but to know where the shackles
that need to be broken, to know where the
weak points that need to be struck
, the word itself lifts the enemies head and
shoulders, the word disarms others and it is important
that the
wars remain that keep this weapon
strong and she believes that such
there will be many more warriors ahead And she
fulfills her poetic function, she is the
author of poetic texts of prose
texts in translations, the author who
used the sword of her weapon is the word,
and this word can continue to work when it is
quoted, when it is spoken, when it is
addressed, when it is not only in the
national language, but also in the language of
literature, and future generations of
authors will also be able to work with this weapon,
and Lesya Ukrainka only makes their blades
in sharper ones. When new words appear,
neologisms of the topic, everything that she introduces into this
language, it then becomes an arsenal for the
next generations,
that is, language and words have many different
functions, this warrior is also among them Well,
yes, Lesya Ukrainka, she is generally such a
visionary about her this Jubilee year
very often talked about as a person who was
incredibly ahead of her time and
despite how cool this text is. It is
very apt, it is sharp, but we
understand how far she goes in
her other genres, because Lesya
Ukrainka is also very often
talked about and written that she lacked a little
Ukrainian language for poetry will pass very
little time will actually pass
in 20 years and the same Pavlo Tychyna from can
do
mind-blowingly incredible things with this language at a time when
Lesya Ukrainka writes poetry, she lacks
this toolkit, it has not been
invented yet, she is trying to
pull it out, but it is
also a very interesting thing. So you read this
text, why are you not a hard cry? And I
remembered
Shevchenko And the dead both the living and the
unborn, this is some such sure
characteristic of great national
poets that they
believe that they will come after them like this, or it is like
Franko's stonemasons,
maybe even we don't know what
this person thought, but as a poet, she believed that there
would be descendants who would accept this legacy and
be able to work with him Better or this
Faith they put their mouths in the theses of their
lyrical heroes and maybe Ivan
Franko himself did not think so, he does not attribute it to himself,
but his lyrical hero is his
poetic voice in the end, that is, here
Lesya Ukrainka writes in the first person and
we can think that this it is a
certain exercise to try to imagine what will happen
next, because the circumstances around her are absolutely
unfavorable for Ukrainian success Oh language,
but she believes in him. And today we will
use many of her formulas,
which work very effectively and sound very fresh
, because for example, now I want to
read a text by Kateryna Kalitko, which
develops a very
Let's say a related topic to what
Lesya Ukrainka proposes, but does it in
2021, and
many people are even typing the first words of
this text, which I will read to myself as a
tattoo. They are becoming so simply
iconic.
So, Kateryna, this is the door.
Here is your woman's language,
shoot her,
protect yourself to the last breath, and
nothing. Don't let them get close,
use the built-in
radio interception system and a night vision device,
all this is inside,
and don’t lie, you can’t
keep track of the location of the enemy and
allow the slightest advance to be shot from a distance, and then they
fall to the crosshairs and don’t delay the
bullets, there are plenty of them, don’t spare
them.
fingers are capable
of motor skills on this and do not
allow it at all let them get closer to the old border
on which the Father's plum lay, when they
cross it, they will have to go hand-to-hand, from
then on, they will cut from
ear to ear with a
bayonet. and
then all at the beginning
Who said that we throw at will, we
armed as much as we could
Well, in general, there are a lot of contexts that can be
unrolled from Kateryna Kalitka, both
from the key translator of
Croatian literature and from the
Russian-Ukrainian War.
after all, there is an emphasis on the power of a
woman's voice and the power of women's
capabilities. And what was
very important to me during this reading was that
Kalitko writes that
you were not left to your own devices and you
actually have a lot in your hands about the
Ukrainian language and the achievements of this language. This is
also the
story of what works on us We do not
invent something now out of thin air it
is not by some tricks, this is the story of a
deep tradition of a distant history that
comes to life today, archetypes,
this is somewhere zaluzhnyy said that when
he looks at the Ukrainian
military today, it constantly seems to him that
some Cossacks, some
Upis,
some Sich riflemen are appearing somewhere, and
this means that simply in
such times, everything is like that works in Ukraine and, in
principle, Kalitko is also very cool, just like
Zhadan, he plays with this sensuality, where on the
one hand there is extreme cruelty, to
which many will say that it is not good for a beautiful
woman to express herself like that,
but
I am sure that Kalitko is saying exactly
what she wants to say, it is well thought out and in the
next line, she says to
her heroine that she said, Stay with your son,
Stay with your husband, that is, there
is poetry in this universe, there is space for both the
private and for understanding what you
can do in a critical situation, and this is
really determined by language if we were to
discuss with you now Ukrainian
literature of the time of independence would therefore be
divided into certain stages related to
various literary contests, phenomena,
generations,
publishing houses, but without fail We would
remember that in 2014, when the
war began, a lot has changed
in Ukrainian literature since then, namely at the level of
themes, because in each poetry collection of each
author, one way or another, we will find some
tiny echo of the war in a larger or
smaller to the extent and actually of Kateryna Kalitku
after 2014, the through-and-through and main
theme of all her texts is war. Although it
can also be said that there is a history of Vinnytsia and
Vinnytsia, in particular, because she is a Vinnytsia
author and this Vinnytsia text is also
present, and I am waiting for
tours of Vinnytsia based on Kalitku's texts to appear and
maybe even from the very gate with
stories about the history of the city and when
her collection of short
prose Land of the Lost appears in 2017, which is noted by
literary critics and various prizes, the collection
about which she is talked about a lot,
continues to be republished because it is very
important and it is Short stories quite special
such Balkan literature as
on translations, you can find traces of
Milenko or many other authors to
whom she turned as a translator, but
those stories are important because they are all about the
war, and in 2018 she will
publish the collection Bunar, at the same time the collection of
Ostap Slyvynskyi, the Winter King, and
the collection of Miroslav Leyuk will be published at the same time the rose and
all these three collections are actually about one and
the same thing, about some vision of a bright
future that will emerge as soon as
Ukraine wins the war, as soon as our
territories are returned to us and we
begin to rebuild some such or
build a state that we dream of and
then around these of three collections in the 18th
year, I had a curatorial program of
poetry at the book arsenal, which
was called Zagorny kingdoms, about this
vision and dream, which is about to be realized
And come to fruition, by the way, you
touch on an interesting topic about how much I have been
written, said and felt then
it seems to me that there is a lot that we can
use Today I remember very well
that your poetic performative
program in and when today I re-read all
these books about which you just spoke, I
understand how much they explain our
present and how much we read less of it
before,
partly because the war really was not a
general great experience, it is the lodge of the
country, and partly because the poetry of good
poets is very condensed and it happens
that you read a certain layer, that is,
in all these books there is also a lot of
love and even a certain eroticism and When you
want you can read them simply as love
poems or poems About where life comes from
or how the world is made up And today
you read them clearly as books my
war and I
want more poetry to be included in the
discourse, somehow we don't have enough time to
talk about poetry about different
poetry, not about the most popular, but I
just know what to take, go back to some
book or take texts that relate to a
certain topic and try to read this topic
through a selection of texts from different
times. We somehow did it today with
you, mother Volya. That is, we just thought we'd
talk mo about texts about language and it was
very broad, but in fact poetry is like a very
dense space in which there is no extra
comma or extra word, extra sound,
extra sound or extra pause.
And I would like to
use it more. Because in the same
poetry of Kateryna, there is a gate in the order of the
silent woman in her last collection, although we are
currently waiting for an even fresher one, which is about
to be published by Meridian-Charnovitz publishing house.
or he was packing some things
or he was forced to move somewhere
or to go to get close to the enemy, the
word we read all this very
clearly, but it surprised me why
such and where such a concentration of this
pain in the author from Vinnytsia, who continues to
stay in Vinnytsia, that is, to Vinnytsia, the
war until 24 February actually did not
arrive. That is, it was something that
happened somewhere in the far east.
Of course, many Ukrainian a they
were proactive, they traveled, they
spoke in front-line cities, at
festivals, they traveled to soldiers, to
volunteers, and so on, but
Can this level of
empathy really be that high? Has it been that high
all these eight years? It is very difficult for me to
say what the level of empathy can be. I
think about I can say
this as a person, not even as a poet. But I
think that good poets have a really high
level of understanding, it is much higher than that of
other people, and it is an opportunity to
immerse yourself in the topic, but at the expense of
political language, sometimes you can go so far
that you are not even close planned to get there,
but poetry proves you and Poetic
text takes you so far
Bohdan, what kind of texts would you like to
read, I have only one left, this is
actually the text from which I started my
thoughts about poems about language, because
in fact it was possible to read and
read any cool three poems
about the language of the native language, the chained eagle, of course, or
about the sails of the grapevine, and that's all
beautiful dream texts But
any good Poetic text will be a
text that we can analyze from the point of
view of language, from the point of view of artistic means,
from how this language works, how
plastic it is, how elastic it is, what it
can offer us, how
moods are formed, but I decided anyway take a
text that tells us something about the
language and I want to read a poem that
tells
us why we should work with the alphabet,
you and I talked about
Antonenko Davydovych last time and
Antonenko Davydovych was among
those who remembered that in the Ukrainian language
in particular, there was the letter g,
he
tried to return this repressed
letter, but he did not succeed,
but the story is not about that, again, the
story is about Abetka, and the last text for
today from me is a poem by Yuriy
Andruhovich,
called Narbutova A 1917,
there is an
epigraph to this text, it sounds so
outstanding graph Georgy Narbut in 1917
in Petrograd begins to create a
high-art version of the national
alphabet,
there is no electricity and no bread and no state
to whom else to bow to the dog, this or the
light, the
fatherland lies double-headed and rusty
and we are learning to write our first letter, the
alphabet begins with an
artery, Assyria, a pharmacy, an
arena, a rank, deep like a coffin, history
screams like an
open alphabet, and like an arfragman, a play like a chorus, a
[ __ ] without an edge, a note pulls someone Aral is
someone's Mount
Athos But you are above us, burnt angel, our first, our hungry bird, our closed And
on the gallows, a feather will fall like
perishable damask on Asia, which has grown
cold,
and the screams of science and writing are like embrasures in the
arches of academies, this is Apollo Who is not in us
or Adam is torn apart, there are no
hospitals, flour, paper,
station wagons, shootings, decrees, the cry of
amphons, the alphabet, we start as if we are learning
to write flashes of red,
I was really impressed by this text.
I
had such an edition at home, I had
several editions and I happened to have a book with
collages of a bird They have attracted me a lot
since childhood, they are kind of
strange and for a child these collages on a black
background were shocking there Before each
chapter Because in fact this book
consists of
exotic birds from the appendix India and between the
different chapters of poems there
Izdrik's collages attracted me very much, but
somehow I always remembered a poem about a Cossack,
Jamaica, which tells here and there, you will
breed, says Cossacks, you will stop everyone in the
fold, but the yoke is given to the neck of my soul.
really,
several years ago, before
Andruhovich's birthday, I wanted to read
Andruhovich and I was somehow just enlightened
by this text, because first of all I imagined
this
Narbut in St. Petersburg, who is sitting and how there is a
dove and a screw, so what are the words in the
Narbut alphabet, we can all do it
see today
thanks to the publisher Savchuk, who made a
wonderful reprint edition, but
this is something very unusual So when you try to
immerse yourself in this antiquity for a job
that has a
luxurious career ahead of it, or
everyone can see from him that he is a talent, that he is just a
person with a very special consciousness and he
reverently and lovingly devotes his
professional time not to create
something like Bauhaus. And he draws the alphabet,
we are not at all used to concentrating on
our own, and I think this is something that
we all learn to this day, it is
not a matter of being proud, but
it is how you love yours. You do not say how you treat
him, and by the way, it is there
somewhere lying around And you know this is my alphabet,
it is such and such there are such and such sounds there are such and such sounds
they work so they combine you
say these letters in words so
many times here are beautiful alliterations
in this digital Andrukhovych I just
read And you try to imagine And what should
this look like the sound it sounds And what
it looks like and the fact that the talented Narbut
devotes so much of his airtime to the
alphabet shows us a simple thing that it is
worth it when we look at
anything made by Narb for the Ukrainian state,
I always have this feeling,
apart from the depth. Besides this tangible
admiration for Narb and Cossack Baroque, I
always have a thought: it is so
cool, it is so attractive, it is worth
paying attention to. Are these illustrations like
that? That is we have already said repeatedly that
Narbut worked for zero and they even have
joint publishing projects, but this is money
from the times of the Ukrainian People's Republic, for example, and it is so beautiful,
or it is our small coat of arms
and
100 years ago we really learned this, we
continue to learn this today, but
I would be very interested somehow ask
Andruhovych how he came up with this text
when he found out about the scar. And who was
repressed, in fact, he was
banned. It is clear that there was a society of
Dan Andruhovych. You could tell all about it.
Maybe even show
some copies of certain images,
but I imagine when you are a young poet and
such a story opens before you
Andruhovych, he really likes
port he has this whole series of
fair portraits and he really likes to
present someone to us
in each of his novels. By the way, he has this,
he has an output of heroes, and he lists
these heroes to you, describes what they are like, and so on.
And I would just like in some a way to
spy on Yuriy Andruhovich's consciousness at the
moment when
the image of Georgiy Narbu appears in
his head and he wants to describe this
difficult time of the revolution, the change of power, it is not
clear what will happen next, but we still
work with our alphabet, we work with
our language, we work with the Academy of Sciences
We are creating an Academy of Arts because
all this should be in the state, and
Andruhovich, through his poetic language,
is able to show this in a very cool way precisely because of
such a state and
in a poem in which the
words are spoken incredibly beautifully, you want to
read this poem. You don't need to read it all.
immerse yourself in a
historical book Although you can, but you will
feel all this through this short poem and
where he begins to tell his I read the story of
Andruhovich and first from the letter a everything
starts with a and until you go through the
complete cycle of understanding And you won’t be able to
go to b so listen, what a cool idea
I got about it, of
course I wish we could read more
narbutov b narbutov VV and so it
could be some kind of biography of
Georgy written by the mouth of Yuriy Andruhovich,
and it could be a cool colorful
question.
I would
still have certain images
in my head at work, yes, at work, to hammer,
yes, on the arbutus, light pink.
from my side, one more text with
which to end our conversation, we have already
talked about the fact that it is so important to appreciate
not only your language, but to appreciate language in
principle and how low it is to make
fun of other languages ​​just because
they are some very primitive jokes and you shouldn't fall
for it.
Well, let's just say they don't
work, they are often ineffective. I
sometimes sin with this. Well, I can honestly say that and
people who read me on Twitter they know
how it amuses me
when you imitate someone like that, certain
peculiarities of Russian phonetics They
amuse me a lot, I can walk the streets of
my beloved Podol and just giggle
at how Russians pronounce certain words,
but I try not to do it too often,
however, there are some cool poetic texts
from the authors who skillfully
practice this, in particular, Artem
Polezhaka has such a poem. We will leave a link
to how Artem Polezhaka, who is currently
defending Ukraine in the ranks of the Armed Forces of Ukraine, how he reads
this text about a Moskal in McDonald's and
about how a Moskal comes to
McDonald's, looks at the window and the menu and
trying to figure out what to order for him
Aha McFlurry cheeseburger bigmak And
spalonicey - that's how Well, and around that
there everything unfolds that he looks and
sees clowns with pistols sees and
looks the other way and sees Cossack
harem pants and this whole fantastic world
grows like this in this McDonald's
where flags are flying, I love it That
McDonald's space becomes hostile for a
Muscovite and he is forced to leave it
They are not happy there and it is very cool. The text is a
humorous piece by Pavel Glazovy
called the speech of the tongue and the cow.
I really like this text. My grandfather came from the
village and walks around the capital.
I don't understand the mug, dear,
show me the one on the side of the strip, what
is the mug here if it's a mug, my grandfather
took the mug in his hands and frowned, you
live in Ukraine and you don't know the language,
the saleswoman was also sharp That poor woman,
I have my own language, I have no
mnemonic, and the wise man said to her grandfather
, you should not be proud of this, because my cow has the same problem, she
has a poor tongue, and she does not know the
language of
Bohdan, she loves this comic very much, she knows it, she
knew it but even as a memory,
maybe somewhere she recited in public
places on public days. But in our house, for
several years
, the humorous stories of Pavel Glazovoi, which were
beautifully republished by Ivan Malkovich,
were re-read in our house, and I and my
sisters and my mother, and everyone had their own
I knew my favorite by heart, because Pavlo
Glazovy is a classic.
And I remembered a much more brutal version against the background of this beautiful
comic strip, because after all, Glazovy is tough, but he is delicate.
really expanded the possibilities of the
Ukrainian language by translating key
authors and introducing them into our context,
I found it
and am thinking of reading it or not, read Bohdana,
please
quote,
they say to Mykola Lukash, you know, in
Lviv there is a Lukash joke for your 50th birthday, I
wonder what the Lukashens say, supposedly
you found a deli, got in line, and
two women squeezed in in front of you, to which
Lukash said
Stop Stop ts anecdotally, this is a commonplace and
it was on Kalinin Square. Near the main
post office at the taxi stop, I got in line and was
reading something to myself. When I saw it, two
boys crowded in front of me.
I shooed them away.
I noticed their statement. I looked at
them and asked curiously where such beautiful
women are hurrying to,
and one of them. And we
don't understand what Lukash is talking about with Khokhlyat calf tongues,
but I'll skip the
insult.
I'll tell you where you're
going. The line roared with laughter, and they licked their tongues like a
cow, sympathy, the line
was on my side, said Lukash, it's interesting
that this story fit quite well in rhyme
and with the humor of Glazovoy, because as we can see,
cow epithets do not leave our
classics, there is a cow, here is a calf. I even
looked at Bohdana's computer to
see how much swearing there is, but she is really
brutal in her podcast, we
don't use such words Well, because we can't,
because she doesn't want to mo Yes, we want to
protect our biofield aura, well, I want
more of this, please.
Nastya just came to visit me. And
in Podol, not far from me,
they are taking a photo of the aura, so you ask. You
ask Nastya, did she do it or
not? their funny
episode is how I went to work at the
Kyiv-Pechersk Lavra and the Institute of Books, the
office of the Institute of Books in the basements of the
Kyiv-Pechersk Lavra, there on the right are
relics, on the left are the Institute of Books, and I
brought two such two metal rods with
which I measured biofields of the Lavra. We have a video of
how Nastya measures the biofield of the
poet Pavel Korbchuk, with whom we also
had to, so to speak
, work together on
all kinds of literary topics. In short,
Nastya and Korbchuk measured everything. I believe
that the biofield can be measured in everything,
so swearing negatively affects our
biofield, and so does the biofield of our
podcast and the microphones will start to rattle
if we start cursing. And we don't want
the microphones of the Motherland to be let down
because they have been
told so far without names And he
still has serious plans ahead, and these plans
stretch like broad fields until the
moment when the
Russian-Ukrainian war ends and we
will continue conversations and continue
conversations until then, and there are still a
lot of conversations because there are so many texts that need to be
read in the shelter of films which series are worth
watching, which series are worth
returning to, and of course, museums that
you want to visit and music that you want to
turn on from various media, but to talk
about all this, we need a little pause, a
little break, as in the academic year,
we finally have a period of spring,
or rather autumn short vacations my
sister always calls
it that, she says I'll take a little vacation for myself, when she was
tired I realized that you and
I have finally reached this stage because it's true,
we're a little tired at the same time I really
want it to be interesting to us because
when we're interesting, you're interesting and it's not
my question ill manners and
immodesty. And the question of honesty is in the
hint because it is terribly felt. We
want the wrong one to change the format, how to find a
certain technique that will allow us to
continue our conversation, but maybe in
slightly different tones or with a slightly different
approach, but I guarantee you that there
will be a lot of
interesting Ukrainian culture, there
will be many conflicting topics, we
have a great language, and I will also remain Bohdana
Neborak I'll be with you too, put stars,
put ratings, likes, please leave
comments, listen to us on
all platforms, write to us, follow
us on Twitter and Instagram
because we are very active there, we will continue to
be active despite the holidays
, let's meet in Chomp and hear each other
[music]